A Finding Aid to the Werner Drewes Papers, 1838-2015, bulk 1890-1990, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Scrapbooks, 1920s-1985; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 5
  Three scrapbooks include fragments of a clippings scrapbook about Drewes from the 1920s-1930s, a scrapbook compilied for Drewes' memorial service, and a scrapbook of photos of artwork and clippings compiled by Rosamund Frost.
  - Fragments, 1920s-1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Memorial Service for Werner Drewes (G3), 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Werner Drewes" by Rosamund Frost (G5), circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, 1897-2015; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 5-6
  Announcements and catalogs are for Drewes' one-man shows as well as exhibitions and events in which Drewes participated.
  Other announcements and catalogs include catalogs listing sales information for Drewes' artwork and announcements and catalogs for other artists.
  Clippings are generally about Drewes and his exhibitions. Also found are 3 children's books published in Germany, one of which was a gift to Drewes as a child.
  - Book, Die Geschichten von Jan und Jon und von ihrem Lotsen-Fisch by Lou Scheper-Berkenkamp (G2), 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Book, Ganz dicht am Main by Marianne Mielenhausen (G3), 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Book, Wie die Tiere Soldated werden wollten by Bootticher and Fedor Finzer, circa 1897; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, circa 1920s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Clippings, 1920s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12-24)
  - Drewes Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1920s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - Drewes Announcements and Catalogs, 1930s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 27-34)
  - Drewes Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1970s-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
  - Other Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1920s-ca. 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
  - Publications, 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17-19)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1890s-2002; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 3.67 Linear feet Boxes 6-9, 16-17
  The bulk of the material is labeled with "R" stickers as the red series and is arranged in numerical sequence.
  The bulk of Drewes' sketchbooks and groups of loose sketches, are dated and titled by subject or genre, and contain primarily pencil and ink sketches, with some crayon and watercolor sketches. Many are labeled with red stickers as the "R" series.
  Also found are 10 folders of Drewes' prints made for holiday greeting cards. An additional folder contains cards made for Maria Drewes.
  Two folders contain artwork by others, including family members.
  - Folder for "Etchings from South America" (G 8), circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Greeting Card Prints, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21-30)
  - Sketchbook, 1912-1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Sketchbook R1: Maine, 1968 September; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Sketchbook R2: Untitled, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Sketchbook R3B: Europe, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook R4: Trip to Europe, 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook R5: France and Greece, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook R5A: Untitled (Mounted Sketches), 1933-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 16, Folder 3
  - Sketchbook R6: Untitled, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook R6: Germany, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook R7: England, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook R7B: New England, 1968 September; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook R8A: Untitled, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook R8B: Life Drawings, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbooks R9 (2 books): Untitled and Life Drawings, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbooks R10 (2 books): Untitled and Life Drawings, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook R11: Life Drawings, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook R12: Figures, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook R16: Untitled, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook R17B: Yucatan and Figure, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 16, Folder 4
  - Sketchbook R18D: Untitled, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook R19A: Luxemburg, Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Oversized material housed in Box 16, Folder 5
  - Sketchbook R20 C: New England, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook R22 C: Untitled, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Sketchbook R23C: Untitled, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Sketchbook R24: Title Illegible, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbook R25B: France, Italy, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Sketchbook R26C: Untitled, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Sketchbook R27C: Untitled, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Sketchbook R31A: Europe, Yucatan, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Sketchbook R35B: Europe, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Sketchbook R36B: France, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Sketchbook R37B: Greece, Europe, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook R38B: Holiday in Norway, Rhine River Trip etc., 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Sketchbook R39B: Untitled, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Sketchbook R40B: Gandria, 1980 July 24; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Sketchbook R41B: Switzerland, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Sketchbook R42C: Untitled, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Loose Sketches R43: Abstract, 1941-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Loose Sketches R45: Nature, 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
  - Loose Sketches R46: Black and White, Nature, 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7-11)
  - Loose Sketches R47: Abstracts, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12-15)
  - Loose Sketches R49: NFS Abstracts, 1935-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16-17)
  - Loose Sketches R50: Abstracts, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 18-22)
  - Loose Sketches R51: Pages from Old Sketchbooks, 1937-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23-27)
  - Collage R55, circa 1970s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Handmade Booklet R56, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook R62: "From My Little Sketchbook, Remembrances of 1970: to Maria", Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Loose Sketches R65, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 31)
    Oversized material housed in Box 16, Folder 6
  - Cards Made for Mary (Maria) Louise Drewes R67, 1960-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 32)
    Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 1
  - Loose Sketches R72, 1930s-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Loose Sketches R73: Nature, Farm and St. Louis, 1934-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Loose Sketches R75: Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 2
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Abstracts, 1930s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Abstracts, circa 1950s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Nature, circa 1940s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8-10)
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Nature, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Old, Mounted, circa 1930s-circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13-15)
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Untitled, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 3
  - Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Untitled, circa 1970s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1915-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 4
  - Artwork by Others, Family Members, circa 1890s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R5A: Untitled (Mounted Sketches) from Box 7, Folder 4, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R12: Figures from Box 7, Folder 14, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R16: Untitled from Box 7, Folder 15, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R17B: Yucatan and Figure from Box 7, Folder 16, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R18D: Untitled from Box 7, Folder 17, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R19A: Luxemburg from Box 7, Folder 18, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Sketchbook R20 C: New England from Box 7, Folder 19, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Loose Sketches R65 from Box 8, Folder 31, Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Cards Made for Mary (Maria) Louise Drewes R67 from Box 8, Folder 32, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Loose Sketches R75: Miscellaneous from Box 9, Folder 3, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Loose Sketches Not Numbered: Untitled from Box 9, folder 16, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others from Box 9, Folder 19, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, circa 1890s-2000; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 5.53 Linear feet Boxes 9-14, 17, MGP 2
  One series of photographis was labeled with black labels and numbered as the "BK" series. This material is arranged in alpha-numerical sequence at the end of the series under the folder grouping "Works of Art in Labeled Series." Other "BK" photographs are arranged alphabetially by folder title with assigned numbers indicated in parentheses.
  Series includes photographs of Drewes, including studio, portrait, family, exhibition and travel photographs. Also found are many photographs, negatives, and transparencies, as well as 8 glass negatives of works of art by Drewes. Many photographs of works of art have corresponding negatives affixed to the back of the photos.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Glass plate negatives have been digitized.
  - Bauhaus Buildings, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Colleagues/Friends, circa 1960s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Exhibitions, 1940s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23-31)
  - Exhibitions, "Harald's AAA Gallery Show and Some of Wolf's Colored Windows", circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Exhibitions, "Sixty-Five Years of Printmaking" (1985) (BK22), Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Family/Friends, circa 1890s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 34-35)
  - In Studio and Teaching, circa 1950s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Interiors of Drewes Home, Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1980s-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Point Pleasant and Wolfram Drewes House, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Portraits of Drewes and Maria Drewes, circa 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in box 17, Folder 6
  - Portraits of Drewes (BK7), 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - School Photograph, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Travel (inc. Manhattan G18), circa 1960s-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Travel: California and Colorado; Europe (Seconds); Guatemala, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Travel: Majorca, Spain; Mexico, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Travel: Peru; Yucatan, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Travel: Peru Documentation, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Travel: Photo Album-U.S.A. Trip, Buildings (BK6), 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Works of Art, circa 1970s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3-32)
  - Works of Art, Negatives, circa 1970s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 33-35)
  - Works of Art, Numbered 1-1500s, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  - Works of Art, Album, circa 1920s-circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Works of Art, Album, circa 1950s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Works of Art, Collection of C. & S. L. Osgood, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Works of Art Given To C. U., 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Works of Art, Slides, 1960s-circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 12-23)
  - Works of Art, Slides by B. Kopp, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 24-29)
  - Works of Art, Slides by Marianne Gurley, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Works of Art, Slides by Marianne Gurley, Extras, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3-7)
  - Works of Art, Slides of Work Bought by National Park Service, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
  - Works of Art, Slides "Steinberg Hall", Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Works of Art, Watercolors Returned from Snyder Gallery, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Works of Art, Wolfram Drewes Private Art Collection, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Works of Art, Transparencies, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14-16)
  - Works of Art in Labeled Series, Archival Resource Key
    - BK2: Photo Positives of Artwork, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - BK3: Photo Positives of Artwork, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 18)
      Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 7
    - BK5: Photo Scrapbook, 1935-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 19-21)
    - BK6: Photo Postivies of Rose Catalogue Artwork, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 22-23)
    - BK8: Photos of Woodcuts, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - BK9: Photos by Marianne Gurley for Book, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - BK10: Sleeves of Glass Plate Negatives of Artwork, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 26)
      (8 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 2)
    - BK11: Photos of Early Paintings, Portraits, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - BK13: Photo Album of Black and White Photos of Artwork, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - BK14: Photo Albums of Black and White Photos of Old "Rare" Pictures, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - BK15: Black and White Photos with Negatives of Artwork, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
    - BK16: Photos of Oils by Drewes, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - BK19: Black and White Photos of Artwork with Negatives, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - BK20: Black and White Photos of Artwork, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Oversized material housed in Box 17, Folder 8
    - BK23: Transparencies by Marianne Gurley, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - BK24: Transparencies by Marianne Gurley, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - BK25: Brigitte Helloth Material, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - BK26: Photos of Artwork, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - BK27: Slide Box File of Paintings, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12-13)
    - BK27: Slide Box File of Paintings, Documentation from original box, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Glass Plate Negatives, Archival Resource Key; 8 Glass negatives (Box MGP 2)
  - Works of Art by Others, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Works of Art by Others, Sold at Auction for Estate, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Portraits of Drewes and Maria Drewes from Box 10, Folder 3, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Oversized BK3: Photo Positives of Artwork from Box 13, Folder 18, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Works of Art in Labeled Series BK 20: Black and White Photos of Artwork from Box 14, Folder 6, Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Mary (Maria) Louise Lischer Drewes Papers, 1930s-1980s; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 15
  Papers provide scattered documentation of Maria Drewes' marriage to Werner Drewes and her career as a jewelry professor and desginer. Correspondence relating to her work prior to her marriage to Drewes, includes her 1957 teaching certificate and letters of reference from the City Art Museum of St. Louis, as well as family letters and diaries primarily documenting European travels during the 1960s-1980s. Also found are notes, a scrapbook and photographs of Maria Drewes' jewelry designs.
  - Correspondence, 1940s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Letters to Family, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - Death Notices, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1960-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 5-9)
  - Insurance Valuation of Jewelry, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Marriage Announcements and Letters, 1950s, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Jewelry, 1930s-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
  - Scrapbook of Jewelry Designs, 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook of Photographs of Jewelry, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1930s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Photograph Album of Maria's Family, circa 1900-circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Jewelry, circa 1970s-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 18-19)